Hello and welcome to this tutorial on how
to install P2Pool and start mining Monero.
P2Pool is a decentralised pool
which leverages a side chain
to manage the active miners and their rewards.
In order to join the Monero P2Pool all you need
to do is run the p2pool software as well as Xmrig.
Before getting started there
are a couple of prerequisites:
Firstly you will need to have Kleopatra installed
We'll have a link for that
down below in the description.
You'll also need a Monero wallet address.
This is so P2Pool has somewhere
to send you precious Monero.
Lastly you'll need to have at
least 50GB of free disk space.
This guide assumes no previous mining experience.
If you already have xmrig and/or the
latest version of the Monero daemon,
you may wish to to look only at
the P2Pool setup and skip the rest.
Before doing anything, we're
going to create a folder called
'monero-mining' in our root
directory on the `C:` drive.
We will be doing everything in
this directory from this point on.
Windows may flag Xmrig as a
virus in the upcoming steps,
so we'll need to create an
exclusion rule for the folder.
To do this we'll need to go to the
virus and threat protection settings.
You can find this by typing it in the search bar
or opening the start menu and typing in `virus`.
Next, under **Virus and
Threat Protection Settings**,
click on **Manage Settings**.
Scroll down until you see the **Exclusions**
Section and choose **Add or remove exclusions**.
Click **Add an exclusion**,
choose **folder** and then navigate to the folder
that you just created in the root directory.
A link to the required installer
for setting up your node and a
connection to the P2Pool side-chain
can be found in the description.
Once you locate the latest release,
scroll down to the assets and download
the installer, shasums and default config.
Datahoarder's public key can
be found on each release page.
Open up a text editor and copy
the public key into the editor.
We can save it as `key.txt`.
Then we'll need to open Kleopatra
and import the key we just copied.
Be sure to use this drop-down to select **any
files** so that you can see the `key.txt` file.
There is no need to counter sign it as trusted.
The important thing is to see a certificate
which matches datahoarder's key.
Next we want to verify the sums file.
First click on **decrypt/verify** and
navigate to the sha file you just downloaded.
We can see that the name on the certificate
matches the key that we just imported.
Now to check that this is in fact the file we
to be installing and not something sinister,
let's go back to our `monero-mining` folder,
`shift + right-click`
and choose **open powershell here**.
Type `Get-Filehash`
and then the name of the file
that you want to get the hash for,
which is this case is the P2Pool installer.
Fortunately we don't have to type in the
whole thing. We can just start typing
"P2" and then press `TAB` and it
will complete the filename for us.
Now we press `Enter`
and it gives us the file hash.
We can now open the shasum file and compare
the hash within to the hash we just generated.
Simply right click and open
with your text editor of choice.
We can see that this hash matches this line here.
Which means that we have a match
and that the file is safe to use.
Alright, now that we've done
that it's time to install P2Pool.
Right-click the install file and
choose **Run as administrator**.
Click **next** until you get to the part
where you choose the install location.
Install it to the same folder
we have been working in.
You'll now need a new Monero wallet address
where you would like your mined Monero to go.
After the setup as finished you'll see a new
folder here in our `monero-mining` folder,
you'll also see a shortcut
has appeared on your desktop.
This is how we will start the P2Pool software.
If you've already downloaded Monero block-chain
either because of a local node or wallet,
go ahead and skip to the next section.
For everyone else, follow this section
carefully and skip over the next section.
Before running P2Pool you will need to make
sure you have enough space on your drive.
During the initial setup we will be creating
a very large file that can easily exceed 40GB.
If you're happy to proceed then you should
run P2Pool by double-clicking the
icon that has just been created.
We are now syncing a database file located in
the p2pool folder with the Monero blockchain.
This could take several hours so let's continue
with the other parts of the setup in the meantime.
If you have followed the steps in
this section there is no need to
view the next section entitled
**IMPORTING A PREEXISTING BLOCKCHAIN**.
So you can go ahead and skip over the next section
and go straight through to setting up Xmrig.
For those of you that already have the
Monero blockchain downloaded to you computer
you will have two options.
The first option would be to copy or move your
files across to the p2pool/lmdb directory.
You'll be able to find your preexisting
lmdb folder in C:\ProgramData\bitmonero.
Copy or move the lmdb folder to the
root of our current p2pool folder.
If you'd prefer not to move or
copy the existing blockchain file,
you can simply tell p2pool where to look for it.
To do this right-click the start.ps1 file,
choose edit,
and go to line 60.
Where it says data-dir we're going
to change this from data-dir=. to
space
and then `data-dir C:\ProgramData\bitmonero\`
We can now save that and close
Now when we use the icon on
the desktop to run p2pool,
it will use the preexisting blockchain files.
This means you'll only have to wait a short
while while it syncs the most recent blocks.
It's now time to install Xmrig. If
you already have this installed then
feel free to skip this section.
Let's head over to the xmrig official
github repository to get the latest release.
The link to this page can be
found down in the description.
There are a lot of options here,
for windows we're looking for the one
that says gcc-win64 in the file name.
Don't forget to download both
of the sums files as well.
For convenience, we're going to download these
files to the same folder we've
been working in up until now.
We're going to verify the
download the same way as before
so I'll move through this process
a bit more quickly this time.
The public key for xmrig can be found in a
different location to the files this time,
check the video description for the link.
Once again we're going to
copy the key into a text file.
We can use the same `key.txt` file from earlier.
Now that we've got our files and the key
we're going to open Kleopatra once again.
First import the `key.txt` file.
No need to countersign.
Next choose **decrypt/verify**
to verify the shasum files.
Finally we need to go back
into our `monero-mining` folder
and get the file hash for the
Xmrig zip that we just downloaded.
Once again, shift+right click
Open powershell window here
Type `Get-Filehash`
and then the name of the file
you want to get the hash for.
This time it's the xmrig zip file,
remember to press TAB to autocomplete.
There's our hash
Now we can open our text editor
and see if there's a match.
As we can see that there's a match between
this line and the has that we just generated.
This means that the zip file is in fact
the one we were supposed to download
and it should therefore be safe to use.
So let's go ahead and open
it and extract the contents.
Before we go any further with our Xmrig
setup, Let's check on the P2Pool software.
It's taken around 8 hours for it to
sync on my machine and now that it has,
it is very important to reboot.
You'll find a timestamp in the description
so you can easily return to this
point in the video after rebooting.
Welcome back.
To continue getting Xmrig set up,
head into the extracted folder.
We're going to run `benchmark_1M.cmd`,
let it run all the way through to
make sure your system is stable.
While this is running it's a good chance
to check that `HUGE PAGES` is enabled.
This is quite important and will
really improve your hash rate.
If it doesn't say `permission granted` there'll be
a link down in the description
to help you solve this problem.
Once that's complete your
hashrate can be found here.
Mine says 2157h/s.
Take note of your hashrate as
you'll need it in just a moment.
To make sure Xmrig is using the
correct configuration when it runs,
datahoarder has kindly put one together for us.
It's the config.json file we downloaded earlier.
But we need to make one slight
tweak before we continue.
In the user section we currently have "x+600000".
We should replace that number with
one equal to 30x your hash rate.
For example my hashrate was 2157,
so I multiply that by 30
and I would put this number 64710 over here.
We can now move this file into the xmrig folder.
Replace the file in the destination.
Let's also create a shortcut for
xmrig and place it on the desktop.
Alright, it's finally time
to get our mining underway.
So let's open p2pool by
clicking on the desktop icon.
We need to wait for it to finish
synchronising before we open Xmrig.
You will know it's synced once you start
receiving block templates and see `depth = 0`.
Finally we can run Xmrig.
Make sure you do this as an administrator.
Otherwise you'll see this
`FAILED TO APPLY MSR MOD` error.
This will negatively impact your
hashrate and quite significantly.
Again, do make sure that `HUGE
PAGES` says `permission granted`.
If it doesn't, check the link
in the description for help.
To check that all you've done is actually
paying off, there's a few things you can do.
Firstly, xmrig should be receiving
jobs from your local ip address.
Secondly you can use console commands
when in the p2pool terminal window.
`status` will print the status of the side
chain, your stratum server and the p2pserver.
If everything went well you should see at least
1 connection under the stratumserver subheading.
It should also report your estimated hash rate.
As p2pool uses a PPLNS system you are
only paid for your effort if you have
a share in this window when a block is minted.
For more information about PPLNS,
please read the blog post by NiceHash
linked below in the comments.
Under the sidechain heading you will see
the number of shares you've submitted and
an approximation of the reward you will
receive once a block has been minted.
As we haven't submitted any shares this
session there is no information available.
Other commands can be found by typing `help`.
For example you can set `loglevel`
which will change how much is being
logged out if you find the
interface a bit too crowded.
Log level 2 is a comfortable
setting for most people.
To set it you can simply type
`loglevel 2` and hit enter.
There are two big incentives
for miners to join p2pool.
First is the low payout threshold and 0% fees.
The other is the ability to sign
up to the xmrvsbeast raffle.
If it's your first time hearing about the
xmrvsbeast raffle, here's what you need to know.
The raffle exists to incentivise miners,
especially those with low hashrates.
It currently does so by pointing large amounts of
hashing power to your node
for a given period of time.
It started quite recently at the begging of 2021
and was set up by an
anonymous group or individual.
They started by setting up their own
pool but with the advent of the P2Pool,
the xmrvsbeast pool was closed and all the
incentives moved to the P2Pool network.
If you would like to take part in the raffle,
the next part of the video covers
port forwarding for this purpose.
In order for the hashing power
of xmrvsbeast to reach your node
you will need to open up your
stratum server to the world.
Port forwarding can be a tricky business,
but in general both your router and your
computer need to have this port forwarded.
Since every router is different, we wont' be
covering port forwarding on routers in this video.
But for Windows, here's what we need to do:
Open the Windows start menu and
begin typing the word "Firewall".
It should be the first result.
Once here, click on **Advanced
Settings** then choose **Inbound Rules**.
Create a new rule.
This rule is for a port.
Click Next.
We want TCP
and then the port number which is 3333.
Allow the connection.
Finally, click next
give it a name, I'll be calling
it stratum, and that's it.
We've opened port 3333 which is the default
port of your default Stratum server.
It's also recommended to open ports 18080
(Monero daemon) and 37889 (P2Pool Peer Network)
for better connectivity with
the rest of the network.
Although this is not mandatory.
Once you have the correct port forwarded
you'll need to head on over to the
xmrvsbeast website linked in the description.
At the bottom of the landing page
you'll find some useful links.
The first is the boost dashboard.
As well as a raffle, there is also
a boost system which provides bonus hashrate
to miners sequentially rather than randomly.
So regardless of your luck you can always
expect a little boost from time to time.
The second link explains in more
detail the rules of the raffle
and provides a page to register which
we will be heading to in a moment.
As well as a page for viewing your
history as a raffle participant.
Select register/update.
This is where you enter the
information required to find your node.
This includes your Monero address
which is used to manage the raffle,
your public ip address and
the port you have forwarded.
The token field should be left
blank for new registrations.
If you don't know your public ip address
you can find it using the powershell
and the command `ipconfig` or you can
more simply check on a 3rd party site.
The websites of VPN providers such as mullvad
or nordvpn are great for this purpose.
A successful registration
should look something like this.
Write down your token, this is important.
We can check double check
our registration has been
successful by heading over to the history page
and entering our XMR address and
the token we were issued with.
If you have any troubles with this
step please head over to the xmrvsbeast
subreddit and search for
similar issues before posting.
A link to this can be found in the description.
You can easily check your progress remotely
by visiting https://p2pool.observer/
Here you can use your Monero address to
search and find your individual progress.
As we're new to mining we'll get an error.
Only once you have begun finding shares will you
see information about your miner and its progress.
To find out how often you may produce shares,
head back to the main page and select
the average share time calculator,
punch in your hashrate and
you'll receive an estimate.
Let's take a look at another
miners progress to see an example.
Here you can see statistics from
the miner including average effort,
blocks found and share positions.
Here the shares move from right to left
with time unlike the p2pool program.
Below this you will see
information about each payout
and the shares which enabled
those payouts at the bottom.
This pool is only possible because
of the hard work of contributors.
The main repository for p2pool can
be found in the description below.
If you're interested to know more
about it's features and how it works,
including how to set things up on a different OS,
this is the place to come.
And at the bottom of this page
you will find a donation address.
The people who work on these things do
it mostly for love rather than money,
so every donation goes to keeping them motivated.
Well, that's all for this video. Thanks
so much for watching and happy mining.
~moneroguides